Let's dive in and start with something fun.
我们开始学习吧 先从有趣的地方讲起
Let's teach you the rules of isolation, the example game we will be using.
现在我们来讲讲孤立棋的规则 我们会用该游戏来示例
Shelly and I will play a game of isolation on a five by five board.
我和 Shelly 要玩局孤立棋 棋盘大小为 5 乘 5
I'll be O and move first.
我是 O 我先走
O gets to place its piece anywhere on the game board.
O 可以在棋盘任意地方下子
I'll choose here.
我要走这
Shelly will be X and she can place her piece anywhere remaining.
Shelly 则是 X 她可以在剩下的位置里任意下子
Shelly, where do you want to go?
Shelly 你想走哪里？
&gt;&gt; I'll go here.
这里
&gt;&gt; From now on, our players move like queens in chess.
从现在开始 我们两个玩家会像国际象棋里的王后那样走动
For example, for my next move, I can go any square that's horizontal or
比如 我下一步可以走任意方格 可以横走
vertical or diagonal from me except I can't move through Shelly's piece here.
直走或斜着走 但不能穿过 Shelly 的这一子
I only have this diagonal move.
我只能斜着走到这里
&gt;&gt; Okay, I get how players move, but do they attack each other like in chess?
好 我知道要怎么走了 但他们会像国际象棋一样攻击彼此吗？
What's the objective of the game?
这个游戏的目标是什么？
&gt;&gt; The objective is to be the last player to move.
目标就是争当最后一个还能走动的玩家
The players cannot go outside the boundaries of the game board, nor
玩家不能走出棋盘边界
through a position that is currently, or was previously occupied.
也不能穿过现在有棋子或之前落过子的地方
The first player to get isolated, and
第一个被孤立的玩家
by that I mean unable to move on their turn, loses.
也就是说轮到哪个玩家了 他却无路可走 那就输了
For my next move I think I will move here.
下一步我要走这里
&gt;&gt; Wait a second.
等等
Why aren't the squares between the start and the end position filled in?
为什么不填上起点和终点之间的方格？
&gt;&gt; You mean these squares here?
你是说这些方格？
You're thinking about the game snake.
你想的是贪吃蛇
In isolation it's just where you land that becomes unobtainable for
在孤立棋里 只有落子处是
future moves.
不能重复走的
&gt;&gt; Okay, in that case I'll move here.
好 那我走这里
&gt;&gt; Great, now we have a game going.
好极了 游戏开展起来了
So let's see here.
我们来走这里
I want to go here and limit your moves for the future.
我想走这里 好堵住你的去路
&gt;&gt; Okay. Okay, so I'll go here.
好 那我走这里
&gt;&gt; Cool.
好极了
I think that what I'll do is try to force an early end to the game.
我想我要试着早早结束这个游戏了
I'm going to do this and start dividing up the board.
我要走这里 慢慢把棋盘分割开来
&gt;&gt; Okay, so there's more spots filled up on the right side of the board, so
好 棋盘右边填满的地方比较多
I think I'll go towards the left so I have more space to move in.
那我往左走好了 左边才有更多的移动空间
Okay, that was a wise move.
恩 很明智的选择
Let me actually go here and see if I can trap you in.
那我走这里 看看能不能困住你
&gt;&gt; Okay. So I'm going to keep going left and
好 那我还是接着往左走
see if I can escape, maybe get back onto the right side.
看看能不能逃出来 看看能不能走回右边
&gt;&gt; Okay, I want to prevent you from getting out.
好 我不想让你逃出来
So I think I can do that, I think I can actually win at this point.
所以我觉得我可以这么走 我觉得这么走我就能赢了
So I'm going to go here and stop your diagonal move out.
所以我要走这里 这样你就不能斜着走出去了
&gt;&gt; Hm, looks like I'm stuck.
唔 好像我被困住了
[LAUGH] I guess I have to try to get out.
[笑声] 我还是得试试看能不能出去
&gt;&gt; Yep, we're getting to end game pretty quickly here because of that
是的 我们很快就要结束游戏了 因为
immediate move where I could partition the board.
我刚才那一步把棋盘隔开来了
So I'll go up here, and now you're stuck and now since you have no move, I win.
那我往上面这里走 现在你被困住了 无路可走 所以我赢了
Yay!
好棒！
Okay.
好了
So what we've shown here is the rules of isolation and the game board.
我们在这演示的就是孤立棋的游戏规则和棋盘
We've also shown some tricks that show about the difficulty of the game and
我们还演示了一些技巧 指出了游戏的困难所在
how you can early on create a partition that divides the boards up into
让你知道你可以在早期建立隔墙 把棋盘分成两半
one side the other and how you often fight for the correct side.
而在这种情况下 通常你都会努力地往正确的那一边走
Strategy for isolation is really quite complex.
孤立棋的策略其实挺复杂的
You'll find out pretty quickly when you actually try do your homework.
等动手做作业 你就知道了